good morning welcome to meditating with
John brevity I'm a cognitive
psychologist and a cognitive scientist
at the University of Toronto where I
teach and do scientific research on
mindfulness and related topics like
Insight flow mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness the cultivation of
wisdom and the aspiration to
enlightenment I've also been practicing
the pasta meditation meta contemplation
Tai Chi Chuan and she come for over 29
years and teaching and professionally
for almost 20 years
welcome if you're joining us for the
first time this is a progressive course
every other Monday is a Dharma day and I
teach practices and principles that we
build on previous Dhamma days so you go
to links in the description you can find
links to previous lessons and you can
catch up the rest of the week that we
meet together and sit and for every day
Monday through Friday on the weekdays
there's a Q&A at the end so we're always
meeting Monday through Fridays at 9:30
a.m. Eastern Time there's Q&A at the end
of all of the sessions including the
derma days please make sure that any
questions you have here are directed
towards the course ecology practices I'm
teaching you if you have broader
questions you know more philosophical
more comprehensive more existential or
stop yet so please direct those to the
live Q&A stream I do every third Friday
3 p.m. each and time on YouTube in order
to help me help as many people with this
as possible please like this video
stream that will raise its visibility on
the YouTube algorithm
please remember that on the 25th which
is the next Monday we're going to
encounter it's going to be a Dharma day
and we are going to start learning how
to practice Alexio Divina it's very
important that you find some sacred
poetry some sacred prose if you don't
know what that means please look the
instructions I gave in yesterday's video
also the video before where I sort of
outline what I mean by those things and
what I mean by sacred so that you'll be
ready to practice well I'll use my texts
the to Mitchell anthologies on Monday
but you'll want to have your own text
ready to go so that you can start
practicing on your own I think that's
everything I need to announce right now
it's it's really wonderful to be here
with all of you I'm really pleased that
like I said how the sang is forming the
quality of the questions that I'm being
given I'm very grateful for that so
thank you
all right I think we're ready so please
get your basic posture please say your
phones to do not disturb and we will
begin what I say begin begin
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best she can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice with your
everyday consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
I think that time for some ah kitty
a lot how does this course compare with
my meditation at bicep and Harris might
be both or did they conflict I don't
know I know that Sam's doing work on
mindfulness and trying to do it from a
completely secular perspective so I
think there's some converse with my work
I don't know the app specifically if
it's a guided meditation practice I
would recommend try not to use the app
very much because things have been
coding specificity you want to get to
the point where you might like I said
it's not about what you're doing in your
meditation and you're sitting in your
contemplation that's what you're doing
in your life that resonates with what
you're doing in your city if it's an OP
that's helping you to remember to
meditate or to practice some principles
perhaps it will be convergent apps that
claim to sort of you know read
brainwaves and tell you when you're
doing mindfulness
I'm as a scientist I'm deeply suspicious
of those I think they're likely not
doing what they claiming to do and so
I've been on the inside when one of
these was being developed and I was very
disappointed what I saw so I don't know
which kind of app it is if you think
it's convergent with you know the core
four with both meditation and
contemplation then it's probably useful
helpful like I said I'm speaking out of
ignorance and I've said if it's this
that's what I'd be concerned about if
it's this that's what I'd be concerned
about I hope that's helpful answer to
you Andre FEA
hello Andre in recent weeks I've
developed the gastric neurosis to
distrust me University work on Varys
already hear that and the end of a long
term relationship oh you're in grief
there there's nothing
harder there's nothing nothing harder
for humans than grief disappointment and
grief when they're in the same family
these are the hardest things the wisest
person I met in person in my life said
to me that there's nothing harder he
wasn't trying to trivial or criminalize
or dismiss but he also said there's
nothing that takes us to the depths of
the humanity he said to me he said don't
get into a serious relationship
he didn't mean romantic he meant
anything friendship with somebody who
has not experienced deep grief because
they there's a there's a there's a
humanizing aspect to that so there was a
woman who came to the Buddha and her son
had died and you know like many people
she assumed the Buddha had miraculous
powers and she kept pestering him she
wanted him to heal and resurrect her son
heal and resurrect her son he kept and
she kept me kept doing that and then she
said okay I will I will help you with
your problem I will heal your son on one
condition
I need you to go into town I need you to
find a house right and go to each house
and knock and asked if they have a
mustard seed she said I can do that he
said wait lately you can only get a
mustard seed from a house that has not
tasted grief not experience death she
said okay and she went and knocked on
the door please the Buddha has offered
to heal my son do you have any mustard
seeds oh yes yes is this host free of
grief as as there is it never
encountered death or loss and oh no I
lost my grandmother oh no my wife oh no
oh no she went from house house house
house and then eventually she went oh
and then she went back to the Buddha and
she said thank you thank you for helping
me see there's nothing that binds us
there's nothing that binds us what that
does
so I'm not trying to paint a silver
lining for what's happening to you
not at all instead I'm trying to explain
to you why I have reverence for what
you're going through and that I'm
expressing as much as I can you know the
connectedness we share in that we have
both experienced deep loss now on to a
more practical question but I thought
the existential is she needed to be at
least recognized and addressed because
very often what we need in these deepest
times nobody can give us advice what we
need is to room we need to experience
that we're seen and heard I now if I a
very painful or difficult to meditate on
these things but still think it's
necessary in order to get rid of the
gastric neurosis since it's caused by
mental state rather than a physical
problem could you suggest any mentor or
specific lessons that could help so the
the difficulty is the stress I think
right
I think meditating on the gastric
neurosis to try and make it go away is a
little bit wrong way to frame it that's
where you're trying to get the
meditation to become a commendable cure
for you I think instead if you really
concentrate on the core for really
getting into your body in a different
way so what instead of trying to you
know get rid of this try to get into a
different way in your body in which it
is not focally present really deeply
don't do anything beyond just really
deeply do the core for really really
really deeply and don't again and just
know and don't even maybe even do the
500 but part of mindfulness on it right
now just note the the pain or note the
stress you just come back and really try
to remember sati what it's like to
deeply inhabit your body in a place in
which these things are not focal so
instead of trying to make it go away I'm
trying to get you to do it really really
fundamentally embodied reframing of how
you're relating to
about the the grief and the chances are
these two things are being deeply
integrated maybe not helpfully by your
brain because they're both you know
conditions of threat and lost they're
both triggering amygdala and they're
both sort of playing with your
reconstructed memory in powerful ways
maybe it's good to talk to somebody
regularly the advice that this person
gave me about grief is he said is that
the only way through grief you have to
grow into a different person
and so the thing to do about that it's
like I say you might consider some
therapeutic interventions I don't know
your particular situation it sounds very
distressing yeah I would increase the
Dharma learning much more a 14 your
aspiration to growth is the best way to
try and slowly slowly slowly because
that's all the only way it will happen
start to move forward so in both ways
what I'm saying is trying to inhabit
your body or inhabit your life
differently than you are rather than
trying to make these things go away and
try to continually remember that you
have gone through this before loss
stress and other people have and again
not a Hallmark card of I can do it but
remember knowledge and acknowledgement
and reverence for the fact that you have
resources within you that transcend your
ego across so I hope that's helpful to
you I really did I really did Rainer
Ludvik for deep the past night
experience one thought after you the
other with no noticeable solid gaps I'm
not sure if it's possible to not think
anything for an active morning any
advice
it is possible that just takes a long
time what about the other way in which
you might be able to get into it when
you meditate
you apply the five factors to inquire in
mindfulness do you get the distraction
going wait you get a moment of where
you're not in thought and then try to
savor that and try to notice that more
often as it as your way of trying to
become more aware of the space between
your thoughts but secondly you need to
do things that get you into the flow
state the flow state is a universal
powerful way of being and in that state
you will not have that thought you'll be
so focused and and coupled to the task
in the environment and absorbed into it
that that will go away and it's and it's
a wonderful state to be in
it's an optimal experience in optimal
performance getting into the flow state
more reliably find activities and
there's activities you can do in in your
dwelling like you can take up a martial
art you can do Tai Chi there's just lots
of things there's books on how to find
flow how to cultivate flow how to
enhance flow because if you can get that
then you can start to create a felt
consciousness a felt memory of what it's
like to be absorbed and involved awake
and alert but without thought running
through your head
harima is it possible to do this
meditation in a busy noisy environment I
cannot keep the focus inside my body but
let go of the tension and all the sound
takes me inside much like a singing bowl
um yeah um it's good to talk to you
again on you yeah you can do that
eventually when you get when you've been
practicing a long time it's very much
like that all the sounds are wrong
I had something very similar as a
metaphor it's like my mind is like water
and the sounds and all I do is just a
rippling through or but I gets very slow
to your ringing of the bowl and I if
you've been practicing for a long time
and you are reliably getting deeply into
this practice then what you describe I
think is something that I myself have
found to be possible within
you know within this practice so it
seems very plausible to me it seems very
plausible to me Dimitar what do you
think about doing Metta on snippets or
sequences of memories that come up is it
like doing better on yourself since your
experiences have shaped you into being
in some way what world can memories and
generals serve within a mindfulness
practice yes yes in fact very often
they're like what you're doing the
meditator questing what will come up are
snippets of memory and yes yeah and then
you treat them as a portal yes but what
you know where did that come from what
is behind that and if you take something
like what you're doing in the meditative
questioning into your meta with those
memories I think you'll find that it
gets you very equally into the practice
Kyra Kroger since I asked the question
about breathing and raising my shoulders
my attention seems hyper focused on my
breath and bringing up the even more
anxiety of not getting a full breath any
suggestions yes so this is a spiral that
some people get into so stop following
your breath
just stop following your breath so
instead what I want you to do is I want
you to do your rooting and I want you to
pay attention to the sense of contact
where you're touching the cushion and
what I want you to do when you're there
is I want you to just right just keep
coming back to that sensation of contact
and rootedness and stability just coming
back forget your breath
forget your breath for now come back and
focus on the contact and the routing and
the stability and the routing and you're
distracted you come back refined the
routing refined that sense of contact of
reaching into the earth of stabilizing
yourself and doing that over and over
and over and over and over again make
that your meditative focus for now then
once that stabilizes then we can
probably shift back you may just go
directly to deepen deep the pasta and
just leave your breathing where it is
for now so we have to bring that up
you're in this this is a parasitic
processing it's spinning on itself and
so the thing to do is just let it go for
now shift the focus as I suggested and
work with that for now so
I hope the answers were helpful to
everyone thank you for joining as I said
the Sanger and the way people are
contributing to it and participating in
it supporting each other is more than I
could have hoped for
and it's a wonderful thing when when
reality exceeds our hopes I want to as
always thank my dear friend in tech from
a Jamar he's always there and I can rely
on him and of course my beloved son
Jason who's again always here for me
always helping it's good to have him
around because he always reminds me who
I really am please subscribe to the
channel to be notified of the next video
on the channel you'll find links to the
lecture series awakening from the Munich
crisis the discussion series voices with
Ravi ki where these topics are discussed
in more depth and connected to more and
more encompassing response to the
meaning crisis and cultivation of wisdom
and a way of life please invite others
who might benefit to to this course to
watching the videos so a pleasure of
that Brett is here often in a Sangha and
he is running the discourse server you
go there you can find a community people
who are practicing this and discussing
it and also discussing wakening from the
meeting crisis voices with ravi key all
of what's happening right now
and some of you have already gone there
and found that this is just a wonderful
community to belong to I think this kind
of platform the kind of community that
are forming around it is where a new
culture is starting to bubble up you
know the actual revolution wasn't a
political revolution there was a
cultural revolution in which people
adopted new psycho technologies and then
new emerging practices and then new
communities and then a new culture and a
new worldview a whole new way of being
human emerged I think something like
that is possible for us right now and
the discord servers are place in which I
think this is starting to show itself
a reminder that we are doing this every
weekday morning at 9:30 Eastern Time
finally remember that continuity of
practice is more important than quantity
of practice there is no enemy worse than
your own mind and body but no Ally no
true friend
greater than your own minded bodies take
care and I'll see you on Monday remember
to get your sacred poetry in your sacred
prose for Lexi Oh Davina bye bye
everyone